Finding Aid for the Percival Bailey Personal Collection of Papers and Photographs Biomed.0339
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Professional and Personal Writings, 1935-1972; Series 3.; 29 folders
  - "Harun al-Rashid"., 1966; 32 p. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    printed as The Chicago Literary Club "Club Paper" LXXIV, 1966; manuscript sheet titled "Haroun ar Rashid", with a quote from Joseph Petulengro [fictional character]
    autobiographical essay; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Apr. 11 1966; also published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969 with title spelled "Haroun al Raschid"
  - Book review of "L'Inconscient" by Henri Ey., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    photocopy of annotated typescript, published in "Archives of General Psychiatry", 17(1):122-126, 1967
  - "The future of neurology"., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    typescript and reprint of a chapter in "Zukunft der Neurologie", ed. by Hans Georg Bammer, Georg Thieme, Stuttgart, 1967
  - "In the footsteps of Esquirol"., circa 1968; 14 p. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    essay on Dr. Bailey's second year of study in France, 1925, when he focused on psychiatry; published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Eulogium discipulorum meorum"., circa 1968; 26 p. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    annotated typescript; two manuscript pages: "Domestic disciples, U.S.A.", and "Foreign disciples"
    short enumeration of the career paths of about 76 of Dr. Bailey's "disciples, that is, men whom I have tried to mould into scholars"; short summaries of the careers of 16 of these individuals; four folders (Box X, nos. XX-XX) contain cover letters, c.v.'s, bibliographies and other documents from many of Dr. Bailey's former pupils, gathered as material for this essay
  - Preface to "Sigmund le tourmenté: une tragédie en trois actes", by Théophile Alajouanine., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    annotated typescript of the English version of Dr. Alajouanine's preface to the French edition of Dr. Bailey's book: "Sigmund the unserene: a tragedy in three acts", Springfield, Ill., Thomas, 1965
- Professional Life, 1949-1992; Series 4.; 18 folders
  - "Discussion of Noordij's paper at C.N.P.A."., 1956 October; 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ground-breaking ceremony for new Illinois State Psychiatric Hospital., 1956 October 19; 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    typescript of Dr. Bailey's remarks
    for photographs, see Box 2, Folder XX
  - Remarks at the 25th Anniversary of the Bobs Robert Hospital, Chicago., 1956 October 13; 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Celebration honoring the retirement of Dr. Lester Dragstedt., 1959 May 28; 14 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    annotated typescript and manuscript pages
    Dr. Bailey was the Toastmaster for the occasion
  - Dedication and unveiling of a portrait of Francis J. Gerty, M.D., 1966 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    typescript of the proceedings, with Dr. Bailey's tribute on p.12-16; photographs of the Gerty portrait, the speakers, and guests
  - Illinois Department of Public Welfare and Department of Mental Health., 1949-1968 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    seven-page typescript historical report, with recommendations for the future, signed by Percival Bailey (ca. 1959), focused on the Illinois State Psychopathic Institute and the Psychiatric Research Council; newspaper clipping on Dr. Bailey's appointment as research consultant to the Dept. of Public Welfare and Director of the Illinois Neuropsychiatric Institute; carbon of typed page headed "Department of Mental Health, Division of Research Services", stating that Dr. Bailey retired in 1967 because of ill health; additional communications, programs, and clippings
    at the time of Dr. Bailey's report he was Director of the Illinois State Psychopathic Institute and Research Consultant to the Department of Public Welfare; for photographs related to these institutions, see Box 2, Folders xxx-xxx
  - "Percival Bailey Museum" of neuropathology specimens., 1973, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    correspondence re. disposition of the collection; news note in Loyola University Medical Center bulletin "Stethoscope" re. the housing of the collection in the Center (March 10, 1981)
  - Speeches and lectures., 1942-1963 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    announcements, programs, and clippings concerning professional and public presentations by Dr. Bailey
  - Articles and clippings about, or mentioning, Dr. Bailey., 1965-1969, undated; folder 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Articles and clippings about, or mentioning, Dr. Bailey., 1979-1992; folder 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    this material was collected by Yevnigé Bailey
  - Tributes to Dr. Andy Hall, oldest practicing Illinois physician., 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    souvenir program to "Dr. Andy Dinner", 1955; clippings
    Dr. Bailey was a "Dr. Andy Baby"
  - Professional and academic miscellanea., 1953-1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    programs, announcements, clippings
  - "Goethe und Freud", by Henry von Witzleben., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    reprint from "Studium Generale", 19(10): 606-617, 1966
    inscribed by the author "To Percy - for his enlightenment (prognosis guarded!), Henry"
  - Career information from Dr. Bailey's former students, U.S. A-D., 1968; folder 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    curriculum vitae, bibliographies, other documents, and letters
  - Career information from Dr. Bailey's former students, U.S. F-J., 1968; folder 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Curriculum vitae, bibliographies, other documents, and letters
  - Career information from Dr. Bailey's former students, U.S. L-W., 1968; folder 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Career information from Dr. Bailey's former students, foreign., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "A psycic [sic] analysis of the American Neur. Ass." by Milt Gross., undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    photographs of seventeen caricatures of eminent neurologists, including Percival Bailey
    removed from black paper scrapbook
- General Correspondence, 1946-1973; Series 5.; 3 folders
  - Various correspondents., 1946-1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    includes notes from Gov. Adlei E. Stevenson, 11/11/52, 11/17/56; Sen. Paul H. Douglas, 1/16/59
  - Orville T. Bailey, M.D., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    letter from O.T. Bailey (no relation) with typescript of his essay "How fair the meadows are today", read to the Chicago Literary Club on Ladies' Night, May 21, 1973
    O.T.Bailey (1909-1998), a neuropathologist, and P. Bailey were both at Peter Bent Brigham Young Hospital in the early 1930s, where their mail was frequently confused; in 1959, PB was instrumental in bringing OTB to the University of Illinois Medical School; they were both longtime members of the Chicago Literary Club
  - Request from Library of Congress for portrait photograph., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Photographs, 1902-1973; Series 8.; 23 folders
  - Percival Bailey., 1914-circa 1971 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    twenty-six studio portraits and snapshots; one pencil sketch portrait - "for Percy, Xmas 1957" [signed, but signature unidentifiable]
  - Percival Bailey and wife, Yevnigé., circa 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    snapshots taken in the Bailey home
  - Early photographs of Dr. Bailey with family and schoolmates., 1910-1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    PB with mother and siblings, ca. age 10; PB and [brother] Paul; PB and siblings at ca. age 18; members of Buckskin School, Beaver Creek Township, Illinois, PB ages ca. 8 and 10; PB and schoolmates, Southern Illinois University, Carbondale, 1910; PB and young lady, Carbondale, 1911
  - Immediate and extended family photos., 1920, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    mother Stella; younger brother, Paul; "Sister Bessie in front"; father, in Army uniform; Aunt Wilhelmina; wife Yevnigé and siblings [?]; views of Hinterstadel, Baden, Germany, where great-grandfather Boehler was born; Mrs. Bailey's cousin Jennie; group shot of "my cousins" including Jennie; [family or close family friends]: persons identified mostly by first names - includes two snaps with PB, taken at the Second International Congress of Neurological Surgeons, Washington, D.C., 1961; PB, Sister Genevieve and sister Bessie
  - Dr. Bailey at the University of Illinois Neuropsychiatric Institute., 1943-1945, 1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    eight snapshots in his office, operating room, with a patient, at microscope, etc.
  - Galesburg State Hospital, Galesburg, Illinois., 1953-1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    PB speaking at opening of Thudichum Psychiatric Research Laboratory, Galesburg State Hospital, Oct. 17, 1953; John Chapman, Illinois Lt. Governor, reading at the 10th Anniversary of Galesburg State Hospital, Oct. 21, 1960; Galesburg, April 30, 1963 - PB and staff
  - Dr. Bailey at the Illinois State Psychopathic Institute., 1953, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    "my girls", Illinois State Psychopathic Institute, 1953; final Christmas Party, 1958 - PB and staff
  - Dr. Bailey at the Illinois State Psychiatric Institute., 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    four snapshots taken at the ground-breaking ceremony for the Illinois State Psychiatric Hospital, 1956; color photo of Francis J. Gerty reading at the dedication of the Illinois State Psychiatric Institute building, 1959 [photo mislabeled as having occurred at the ground breaking]; first operation at Illinois State Psychiatric Institute - Penfield, Bailey, Rudy, Barchiesi at window; Penfield, Evans, Bailey at window; PB with crown of leaves "Celebration after operation"; views of the Institute Buildings; Clinicopathological Conference, March 28, 1961 - group photo with PB; presentation of PB's portrait to the Institute, Oct. 21. 1961 - Dr. Bailey at microphone; composite of twelve male portraits including PB - Illinois Psychiatric Research and Training Authority, 1964; group photo at the signing of the law setting up the Psychiatric Training and Research Authority, with Governor Stratton, Representative van der Vries, and Drs. Bailey, Bettag, Garner, and Genty
  - Dr. Bailey's birthdays., 1961, 1962, 1963, 1965 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    snapshots of Dr. Bailey with co-workers and friends
  - Dr. Bailey with colleagues and friends., 1951-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    PB with Miller and Strauss, ca. 1951; three photographs of Warren McCulloch, PB, and Gerhardt von Bonin in various laboratory settings, ca. 1940; PB and Illinois State Hospital superintendants, 1952; PB and [probably] Dr. Schaltenbrand, Würzburg, 1953; PB and colleagues, entrance to the Academy of Medicine, Seville, Spain, Sep. 1953; PB and Marianne Simmel, Oct. 1954; Officers of the American Neurological Association: PB, Bucy, Vanderahe, Merritt, Rupp, 1955; PB and Dr. Schaltenbrand, Apr. 1956; PB and Mr. Barsumian looking over plans for Armenian Church; PB and Paul Bucy in back yard, 1960; PB and N.I. Grashchenkov, Prof. of Neurology, Moscow, Sep. 12, 1960; Dr. and Mrs. Bailey and unidentified man in gardens at Charenton, 1962; PB and Ruby, Masier, Massserman, Grossman, Marky, Kelly, Gerty, Smith, Sugar, Grinker, Richter, Bucy, Klüver, Oct. 1963; PB and Residents Graduating Class, June, 1965; PB with experimental psychology staff; PB and John Lee
  - Portraits inscribed to Dr. Bailey., undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Heinrich Klüver; Otfrid Foerster; Henri Baruk
  - Boyhood friends., undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    portraits of Lester Dragstedt, Guy Gladson, Guy Karraker, W. W. Vandeveer, and various snapshots
  - Society of Neurological Surgeons meeting, Phoenix, Arizona., 1971 February 16 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    four photographs; one group includes Drs. Green, Nielsen, Sugar, Bucy, French, Sweet
  - Latin-American Neurosurgical Congress, Montevideo (Congreso Latinoamericano de Neurocirugía, 6th)., 1955 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    three photographs: PB at speaker's table; landing at Montevideo with Suzanna Ravecca; with Dr. Arana at his home
  - Portraits of French psychiatrists and neurologists, etc., undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Henri Baruk, 1897-1999; Jean-Martin Charcot, 1825-1893; Henri Claude, 1869-1945; Gaetan G. de Clérambault, 1872-1934; Pierre Janet, 1859-1947; Louis René Bréhier, 1868-1951 [historian] - newspaper clipping
  - Portraits of Dr. Bailey's students., 1954-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    forty-one identity photographs from various years: William Adams; John Andrew; Chisato Araki; Jose Barras; John Blundell; F. Keith Bradford; Paul C. Bucy; Theodore J. Case; Jerzy Chorobski; Jose M. Cid; Ralph Cloward; Marul[?] David; Carl J. Graf; Sidney W. Gross; Wesley Gustafson; Wallace B. Hamby; Henry Harkins; W. Tracy Haverfield; Rei Hayashi; Harold E. Haymond; Jesse Hermann; Kenji Kanaka; Stephan Környey; Fred Kredel; Adolfo Ley Garcia; Paul M. Levin; Miserocchi; John E. A. O'Connell; Ivan Perez; Pierre Pnech [?]; Manuel Sanchez; Arist Stender; William H. Sweet; A. Earl Walker; James W. Watts; five unidentified photos
  - Photographs of Japanese students and colleagues., 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Dr. and Mrs. Shozo Kito; Dr. Shigeo Okinaka; Dr. and Mrs. Y.S. Kim; Dr. and/or Mrs. Bailey with Dr. and/or Mrs. Morii, 1965; Dr. Chisato Araki and family; Dr. Tanaka and son; scene in operating room, with notation "The first memorial craniotomy at my own clinic since I returned, 1953" - but no identification
    for 1953 letter from Y. Kim to Mrs. Bailey, see Box 1, Folder XXX; additional photos of these and other Japanese colleagues can be found in other folders
  - Photograph album., 1928-1948 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    p.1: PB portrait, 1932; PB and Dr. Schaltenbrand, Würzburg, 1938; p.2: Luzon, 1948; p.3: PB at Pathology conference, Billings, 1933; Lester Dragstedt, 1933; p.4: Luzon, 1948; p.5: Dr. Eisenberg, Wien; p.6: Luzon, 1948; p.7: Bremer and apraxic patient; Rei Hayashi, Billings Lab.; p.8: Shimizu and Tanaka, Kamakura, 1948; priest in garden near Great Buddha, Kamakura, 1948; p.9: Sanchez, Baz, Bailey, Mexico, D.F., 1943; p.10: Kamakura; p.11: Reese, Bailey, Waltman, Kansas City; p.12: Bailey and Araki, Kyoto, 1948; p.13: Nan Thomas; Florence Cloward; p.14: Kyoto; Kamakura; p.15: Bessie and Sister Genevieve, 1939; apartment, 1413 E. 57th Street; p.16: Kyoto, 1948; p.17: Mexico, D.F., 1943; p.18: Araki's wife and daughter; PB, 1942; p.19: PB, 1932; PB, Lab., I.N.I., 1942; p.20: Rhine, McLeensboro, Ill.; George Schaltenbrand and children; p.21: PB, lecture, U. of Ill. 1950; Bailey and Ectors, Lab., Billings Hosp.; p.22: Bailey, Cloward, Waikiki Beach, 1948; PB off Waikiki, 1948; p.23: PB, Surg. Lab., Brigham, 1928; p.24: Sister Genevieve; Honolulu, Governor's party; p.25: Walker, Haverfield, Bailey, Lab. Billings; p.26: Florence, Ralph, PB, Honolulu; Cloward Family picnic; p.27: Frederic Bremer, Brussels, 1946; p.28: Cloward, off Waikiki; p.29: George Schaltenbrand, inscribed to PB, 1948; p.30: Oahu, 1948; half page: [bearded male in foreign military uniform, Red Cross band on arm - unreadable signature]; verso of half page: Cloward and daughters, PB, Oahu, 1948; p.31: Martha Buck, my teacher; p.32: Waikiki, 1948; p.33: Basil Coleman, Hyatt Harvey; p.34: Araki and family, Kyoto, 1948; p.35: PB, Surg. Lab. Brigham, 1928; Shimizu and family; Shimizu and wife; p. 36: Araki and family, Kyoto, 1948; p.37: Bill and Gerry Guyton; Billy Guyton; p. 38: Surgical Staff, Kyoto University, 1948
  - Disassembled photograph album #1. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    p.1: postcards: log cabin where Pres. Lincoln' parents were married, Kentucky; Mississippi River from Ft. Kaskaskia; First Capitol of Illinois, Kaskaskia; Pierrie Menard Home, Ft. Gage, Illinois; p.2: PB and surgical nurse's at her 20th anniversary party; Sister Mary Genevieve; home of Miss Martha Buck [teacher] taken 40 years later, Highland, Illinois, 1952; Christmas card with two photos of Cpl. Percival Hamilton, 1943; p.3: female portrait [Mrs. Don Sands?]; group shot, Leon Ectors and the King of Belgium; p.4: portrait of George Boris Hassin in military uniform, 1920; Dr. Hassin in Russia, 1920; "Greetings from 3 generations of Bassoes [?]"; p.5: Andrew Ivy, Rush [Medical School], 1922; portrait of unidentified young man
  - Disassembled photograph album #2. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    p.1: inscription on marble plaque at entrance of Neurological Institute, Lisbon; postcard of Chateau de Chalouse, "Country house of Alajouanine"; p.2: Otto L. Bettag, "1st lecture", 1960; Slicer and Morrisey, "Tweedledee and Tweedledum"; p.3: Dr. Norman Dott [neurosurgeon, 1899-1973; Dott and unidentified man at the unveiling of Dr. Dott's portrait, 1960; p.4: PB and two unidentified men, Veterans Administration Hospital, August 2, 1954; p.5: 90th birthday of C. Judson Herrick. Oct. 5, 1958 - group photo, members identified; Peter Virag [Chicago Jewelry store owner]; portrait of Dorothy Schmidt Galloway; Edward Artin, son of "Ol Doc Artin"; p.6: "the first furnischädel [?] I operated on, Brigham [Hospital], 1922, PB"; p.7: operation in unidentified operating room; p.8: three snapshots - "70th birthday, Miss Tress, Miss Muromski, Miss Kahn, May 9, 1962"
  - Disassembled photograph album #3., 1936-1965 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    p.1: Heinrich Klüver, Xmas 1962; Cannon Payne; painted portrait of Sir Francis Walshe [1885-1973, British neurologist]; man in front of Bailey portrait [Bucy?]; snapshot of man, 1936; p.2: three snapshots from Masserman's 60th birthday party, March 5, 1965 - identified are Dr. and Mrs. Bailey, Rioch, Dr. and Mrs. Bashes; p.3: Presbyterian Church and Baptist Church, both in Evanston, Illinois; unidentified building [church?]; p.4: Michelle and Mary Bush, Yokosuka Naval Hospital, Japan, Dec. 8, 1965
  - Disassembled photograph album #4. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    p.1: group photo, including Dr. and Mrs. Bailey, outdoor setting; p.2: three shots of banquet head table, Dr. Bucy speaking, Dr. Bailey receiving an honor from German Consul Matz, Feb. 28, 1962 [occasion unidentified]; p.3: informal group of attendees at scientific conference, Drs. Bailey and Y.S. Kim in center front; small snapshot of Drs. Kim and Bucy at banquet, same conference [occasion unidentified]; p.4: Dr. Heinrich Klüver, July 24, 1965; unidentified male head shot; two snapshots of PB with unidentified males, one dated May 1957; snapshot of "oldtime motel"; large group of doctors and nurses, unidentified, circa 1920
  - Snapshot album., undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Old hotel in Elizabethtown, Ill.; Dr. and Mrs. Bailey, Baptist Camp Meeting Ground, So. Ill.; Guy Karraker readied for a Dongola, Ill. celebration - two pictures; old house where escaped slaves were hidden, So. Ill.